<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jhfoxliu.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jhfoxliu.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-02-05T05:26:08+00:00</updated><id>https://jhfoxliu.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://jhfoxliu.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://jhfoxliu.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jhfoxliu.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">The iMVP project</title><link href="https://jhfoxliu.github.io/blog/2022/stories_iMVP/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The iMVP project"/><published>2022-03-07T01:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-07T01:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jhfoxliu.github.io/blog/2022/stories_iMVP</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jhfoxliu.github.io/blog/2022/stories_iMVP/"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://github.com/jhfoxliu/iMVP"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">interactive epitranscriptomic Motif Visualization and Sub-type Partitioning (iMVP)</code></a> project is a by-product in my m5C studies. At the end of 2021, the days I was trying to set up a deep-learning based classifier for m5C sites, I was wondering about if I can know the composition of the input data of the k-mers sequences. So I tried to draw them on a 2D plane to visulize them. The direct way to do so is firstly converting the sequences into <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">one-hot</code> encoded ones, just like what we do in deep-learning. Then it is normal for us to use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">UMAP</code> and other methods to project them. Most guys might stop here. With the labels, the problem should be already solved. But I noticed that, <strong>if we can find out the regions on the 2D plane with higher densities, we can directly find the sequence patterns from the projections!</strong> I hence began to find some <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">unsupervised clustering methods</code> to extract the clusters. I finally found the best partner for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">UMAP</code> - the powerful density-based method <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">HDBSCAN</code>. With such a combination, I developed a lot of applications in RNA modification motif research. In practices, this framework exhibit ultra-high sensitivity and analysis capacity. I have finished an analysis of &gt;500 million k-mers for &gt;1500 million A-to-I editing sites. I guess this frame work can bring a revolution in the field.</p> <p>I made an important decision in this project that everything should be transparent and clear. It is a good tendency that the academia is seeking for better reproducibility. We are now asked for more and more details about our experiments and analysis in the study. So why don’t we make everything ready for that at the every beginning? I made a lot efforts about this:</p> <ol> <li> <p>I use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">notebooks</code> rather than stand-alone <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">scripts</code> in this study. So that others can repeat my jobs easily and can preview the outputs.</p> </li> <li> <p>I generate and store the raw data used for each plot in the analyses. So that I will no longer need to fetch everything before I sumbit my manuscript.</p> </li> <li> <p>I try to prepare everything according to NPG’s guideline.</p> </li> <li> <p>I will try to set up a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">container</code> of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Docker</code> to keep a stable enviroment.</p> </li> </ol> <p><br/></p> <p><br/> <a href="/blog/"><u>Back</u></a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="story"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A revolutionary by-product]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Be the best in bisulfite analysis</title><link href="https://jhfoxliu.github.io/blog/2022/stories_bisulfite/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Be the best in bisulfite analysis"/><published>2022-03-04T01:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-04T01:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jhfoxliu.github.io/blog/2022/stories_bisulfite</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jhfoxliu.github.io/blog/2022/stories_bisulfite/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="terminate-the-controversy-in-mrna-m5c">Terminate the controversy in mRNA m5C</h3> <p>I have been working with mRNA m5C for over four years, unbelievable. We began our research at the end of 2016, when the workflow of RNA m5C was not optimized. As other competitors, we were curious about the existence of mRNA m5C.</p> <p>There were some challenges for us at that time:</p> <ol> <li> <p>firstly, the commercial kit is optimized for tRNA and rRNA BS-seq, but not for mRNA. With the standard protocol, we often have a conversion rate between 95% to 98%. Such a condition is fine for known sites in tRNA and rRNA, however, it’s disaster for us while applying it on mRNA. Based on binomial distribution, when the number of cytosines increase, we much more chance to get artifacts.</p> </li> <li> <p>the bioinformatic tools available far from satisifying us. They are not fast enough, noisy, and heavy. Although most of the software are open-source, we are hard to modify their codes without fully understanding the logics behind them.</p> </li> </ol> <p>So our decision was to optimize the protocol (by <strong>Dr. Tao Huang</strong>) and to try to set up a new pipeline (by <strong>me</strong>). I guess Prof. Zhang did not expect such a huge project at that moment. In fact, we firstly began with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">meRanTK</code>, but I gave up after several days. It so lucky that we had the tools for setting up one - we had the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Pysam</code> API of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">htslib</code> (or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Samtools</code>) to handle the reads. That’s enough for us to translate our logics into codes. In the the Spring Festival of 2017 (yes, I love the long holiday), I gradually finished the prototype of the pipeline. To accerlate the computation, I introduced <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">multiprocessing</code> into the pipeline, for which I suffered a lot for the synchronization issue.</p> <div class="row mt-2 text-center"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories/stories_bisulfite/three-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories/stories_bisulfite/three-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories/stories_bisulfite/three-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/stories/stories_bisulfite/three.jpg"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The m5C group. The lady, Wanying Chen; the handsome boy Dr. Tao Huang; the groomsman, me. (2019) </div> <p>But we were stuned no long after we prepared to send our manuscript. Just after the holiday, <a href="https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-016-1139-1">the first mRNA BS-seq profile paper</a> published on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Genome Biology</code> (Amort et al., 2017), pointing out that there can be thousands of m5C sites on mRNA in mammalian cells. No long after the first publication, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/cr201755">another paper</a> published on May reported that in HeLa cells and mouse tissues, thousands of mRNA m5C sites are contributed by NSUN2. Things got more interesting in July. The third paper published on <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5580717/"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Genome Res.</code></a> from Frank Lyko (he set up the first transcriptome wide BS-seq protocol in 2008), argued that the mRNA m5C sites found in mammalian transcriptome were not real and just came from the artifacts caused by insufficient conversion, beacuse they didn’t find a convincible stoichiometric measurement for mRNA m5C.</p> <p>We were scooped, but nowadays, I thanks for the scoop. We have to make a break or our works will be meanless. It forced us to turn to optimize our pipeline. In fact, in Lyko’s paper, they used some filter assembled what I used in my final pipeline (something like C-cutoff, but not systematically). The had beautiful experiments. If you zoom in the motif in the main figure, you can indeed found a 3’ G-rich motif (but they ignored). The major problem is, they missed in data analysis: they made mistakes in dropping the multiple alignments, which resulted in a great loss in m5C sites. And this is my conclusion based on my analysis of the differential sites between our pipeline and theirs. During the optimzation, I introduced other features, like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Gini-index</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">signal-noise ratio</code>, which are very helpful in the analysis. In our paper accepted by <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NSMB</code>, we sucessfully clearified that NSUN2 is indeed a mRNA m5C writer for tRNA-like sequences. And thanks Alexandra Lusser for the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41594-019-0217-y">comment</a> on the same issue.</p> <p><br/></p> <h3 id="set-up-a-new-paradigm-in-nsun6-study">Set up a new paradigm in NSUN6 study</h3> <p>It was just the beginning of our mRNA m5C journey. In our <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NSMB</code> article, it is obvious that except for NSUN2, there should be another enzyme contribute to the methylation (also mentioned in the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41594-019-0217-y">comment</a>). This enzyme should favor a 5’m5CUCCA-3’ motif. And now we know that this enzyme is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NSUN6</code>, another NSUN protein responsible for tRNA 3’ end methylation. It’s another story that three papers about that crahsed within two months for that…</p> <p>But, don’t you think it’s boring? If the story is: we found a new enzyme; we had some barplots; we drew some lines, some boxplots, and some scatters; we had some Western Blots; and so on.</p> <p>It’s fortunate that we have a the crystallization of NSUN6-tRNA complex! In Nov. 2018, <strong>Kappel</strong>, a Ph.D. student (now a Post-doc in Broad institute) from <a href="https://daslab.stanford.edu/">Das Lab</a> published a RNA-protein complex simulation method (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RBP-denovo</code>) based on <a href="https://www.rosettacommons.org/software">Rosetta</a>. This method enable us to predict the folding status of RNAs dock to a protein. Personally, I love <a href="https://fold.it/"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Foldit</code></a>, and I am a long-term computational contributor to <a href="https://boinc.bakerlab.org/"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Rosetta@home</code></a>. It’s a great chance for me to try so!</p> <p>After a short struggle, I successfully set up Rosetta and figured out how I should do (in a mid-night, 5:00 am). Then I integrated a lot of protein simulation (comparative modelling), and RBP folding in the study. I found two possible models for NSUN6-mRNA complex: (1) mRNA might interacts with NSUN6 in a tRNA-like shape, or (2) mRNA laid tightly on the surface of PUA domain. To clearify the model, I schemed some mutagensis experiments to verify that, and I finally made sure that a tRNA-like process should be more reasonable. I also tried to use the predicted structure to guide us to design a NSUN6 variant that can distinguish mRNA and tRNA.</p> <p>I guess this should be a new paradigm for us in RNA modification study: with simulation, we can focus on some residues of the RBPs, and we can design proteins to help us understand the biological processes. No long after my trials, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AlphaFold</code> published its achievements.</p> <p><br/></p> <h3 id="three-years">Three years!!!</h3> <p>In fact, we initiated our developmental mRNA m5C study half a year before the NSUN6 study. I don’t remember why Prof. Zhang decided to profile m5C in embryos at that moment. But we underestimated how long we will spent on it.</p> <p>We won the bet. There are indeed a great enrichment of mRNA m5C in the embryos. It should be surprising, We guessed we had the chance to be accepted by the top journals. Yes, we did, closely.</p> <p>We firstly submitted it to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Nature</code>, on the January of 2019. Our article was successfully sent to the reviewers, however, none of them seemed to have a practices in mRNA m5C. After the rejection, we sent the manuscript to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Science</code>. We entered the revision, but was just the beginning. One month latter, we received a 17-pages long comments. One of the reviewer, revised everything, even a comma, in our manuscript (I admired to him/her so much and this reviewer made a great impact on my working style). The major concern from the reviewers was that some of our conclusions were not purdent enough. We took a long time to handle these issues. However, we were scooped agian. Yang et al. published <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31399345/">a similar paper</a> on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Mol. Cell</code> a head of our re-submission. We were rejected. We then tried <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NSMB</code> but the reivewers didn’t support our publication.</p> <p>We decided to append some data (from human) and modify the paper to be a purely resource paper. We merged the evolutionary analysis we planned to publish independently in the new version. But this time, our manuscript failed to enter a revision sections. We tried many many journals. We were exhausted and sent it to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Nat. Commun.</code> finally on <strong>September, 2021</strong>, over 2.5 years after we had the first submission. Luckly, two of the reviewers gave us positive comments, but one of them seems unpleasant. He/she had only one comment that we should provide the stoichiometric reulst for the data, although that was totally not necessary. We carefully modify our manuscript and resubmitted to the editor. After &gt;50 days’ suffering, we eventually received editors’ email telling us the manuscript was in principle accepted. I feel numb, rather than happy. Now we were liberated.</p> <div class="row mt-2 text-center"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories/stories_bisulfite/finally-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories/stories_bisulfite/finally-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories/stories_bisulfite/finally-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/stories/stories_bisulfite/finally.jpg" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories/stories_bisulfite/celebration-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories/stories_bisulfite/celebration-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories/stories_bisulfite/celebration-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/stories/stories_bisulfite/celebration.jpg" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Cheers! </div> <p><br/></p> <h3 id="the-hard-road-of-mrna-m5c-study">The hard road of mRNA m5C study</h3> <p>It’s 3 years past after we published our first m5C paper. Our pipeline stands in <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41592-021-01280-7"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">third-part tests</code></a> and is graduately acknowledged by other labs as a <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkab1075"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">gloden standard</code></a>.</p> <p>If I have to estimate the progress in these field these years, I might answer that, probably we just jammed. It’s still hard for us to learn the the <strong>real</strong> biological role of m5C and other modifications. We don’t have suitable techniques to exclude unwanted interferences in our experiments and analysis. For example, we often don’t have consisted methylation changes when somebody claims that m5C might involve in mRNA stablility control; although we have data showing that m5C can indeed have higher affinity with ribosomes, we don’t biophysic data to support our conclusions; we are unable to split the functions of mRNA m5C and tRNA m5C; we have no idea to figure out the function of single site modifications; … We don’t agree to some of the conclusions by other groups, but that’s not welcomed to have battles in this field, unlike that in evolution.</p> <p>This field changed in these years. The editors and reviewers ask for functions more and more frequently. However, we don’t have enough data to support a clear “function” for most of the cases. We are strict with our conclusion, but we are unable to let others be prudent. The field, mRNA m5C, is too young for those requirements.</p> <p>Sadly, our m5C group (me, Dr. Tao Huang, and Wanying Chen) are going to leave. We have tons of data, but we have no time to completely tide and publish. We are waiting for our followers to finish them. Maybe I will be back, when I have new paradigm for it.</p> <p><br/> <br/> <a href="/blog/"><u>Back</u></a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="story"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Started by accident, be best with insistence]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">As a beginner in academia</title><link href="https://jhfoxliu.github.io/blog/2022/stories_beginner/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="As a beginner in academia"/><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jhfoxliu.github.io/blog/2022/stories_beginner</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jhfoxliu.github.io/blog/2022/stories_beginner/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="igem">iGEM</h3> <p>I have once worked in the iGEM team SYSU-China, where I work as a trainee of the interlab study in <a href="http://2014.igem.org/Team:SYSU-China">iGEM 2014</a> and a team leader in <a href="http://2015.igem.org/Team:SYSU_CHINA">iGEM 2015</a>. I am also a judge for CCiC (Conference of China iGEMer Community) in 2017. The experience playing with iGEM is a real treature for me: I learned how to collaberate with others and how to quickly browse articles in a broad range of topics.</p> <p><br/></p> <h3 id="be-a-member-of-the-zhang-lab">Be a member of the Zhang lab</h3> <p>I was so fortunate to meet <strong>Prof. Rui Zhang</strong> in 2015, when he was just back to China and planning to set up his own laboratory. We discuessed about the research interests (RNA editing, single cell, etc.) in the empty laboratory (now our Room 416). And I decided to have my Ph. D. at the Zhang lab. Look back, it is absolutely a right decision that my achievements today are built on the autonomy and ability of execution I have at the Zhang lab.</p> <p>I never feel shame to tell others that I have a lot of failed projects, much more than my publications.</p> <p>My first project is to set up a algorithm for RNA editing level prediction based on the miRNA editing data, where we believed that the uniform pairing feature of miRNA can make us easier to learn the meachanism of RNA editing behind it. I started to learn programing (sadly, courses in SYSU is out-of-date and we have not been taught before). I gradually grasp <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">R</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Python</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Linux</code>, after some disatsters beginers will meet (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">rm -f</code>, unlimited disk writing, etc. :stuck_out_tongue_closed_eyes:). Of course, we did not finish that project, and nobody achieve it upon now.</p> <p>No long after that, I initiated my undergraduate thesis project: set up Drop-seq by myself. That’s in <strong>2015-2016</strong>, we don’t have any agent for the materials in China. We bought the pumps, the magnetic mixer, the beads, the oil, and any other requirements. I transported the chip from Macow. I isolate the cells and set up everything by myself. Our purpose is to capture miRNA in a single, but the first thing is to repeat Macosko’s experiment. I also have to set up the compuational pipeline in our server. I finished my thesis, but we finally give up the project for the cost and incompatibility of the reagents. Of course, nobody achieve it upon now.</p> <p>The third project before I became a Ph.D. student is to build the home page and the database (miREDB, miRNA editing data base) for our publication (Genome Res., 2018). As a beginner, I had no idea about <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">HTML</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SQL</code>, and espcially the backend. That is the Spring Festival in 2016. I locked myself in my room for two weeks. I tried to learn the full-stack processes of building a website from the backend to the front by reading the tutorials online. And, I survived. I got out of my room with the prototype of them. Latter, they are deployed in our server. (Sadly, these two websites were shut down due to our School’s “Website Security Policy”)</p> <p>Then I move to my Ph.D. career.</p> <div class="row mt-3 text-center"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-1"> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-1"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories/stories_beginning/sever-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories/stories_beginning/sever-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories/stories_beginning/sever-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/stories/stories_beginning/sever.jpg" data-zoomable=""/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-1"> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> My comrades, the two severs. </div> <p><br/></p> <p><br/> <a href="/blog/"><u>Back</u></a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="story"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Starts up as most of the guys]]></summary></entry></feed>